H. P. & E. Day, Inc. Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
H. P. & E. Day, Inc. Records.
1854-1955.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
H. P. & E. Day, Inc.
5.0 linear feet
H. P. & E. Day, Inc., of Seymour, Connecticut, manufactured hard rubber for pens and mechanical pencils. Records include administrative records, product orders and inventories, property and legal documents, financial records, and examples of the company's products. Also included is information about the predecessor and successor companies, Austin G. Day Company and Waterman Pen Company.
MSS19880027
History
In 1854 Austin G., Julius, and Henry P. Day and Thomas Sault founded the A.G. Day Company in Seymour, Connecticut, which manufactured small household and office items from molded hard rubber, particularly pen and pencil holders. In the 1860s the firm began making insulated telegraph wire. In 1870 A. G. Day Company produced 100 miles of wire while another firm, Julius Day Company, took over the manufacture of small rubber goods. By 1876 the rubber company was known as H. P. & E. Day Company and run by Julius's sons Henry P. and Edmund Day. The company was incorporated in 1902 and thereafter known as H.P. & E. Day, Inc.
The company rubber works formed the basis of a new enterprise for the L.E. Waterman Pen Company of New York. Lewis Edson Waterman, pioneer of the production of hard rubber fountain pens, established the company in 1884. The principal parts of the pens were produced at H. P. & E. Day, Inc., at its Seymour plant. This arrangement continued until 1946 when H. P. & E. Day, Inc., became a wholly owned subsidiary of the Waterman Pen Company.
Scope and Content
The H. P. & E. Day, Inc. Records include administrative records, product orders and inventories, property transaction and legal documents, financial records, and samples of pens, mechanical pencils and accessories. Also includes information related to the Austin G. Day Company and the Waterman Pen Company, H. P. & E. Day's predecessor and successor companies.
Arrangement
Series I: Administrative records ( undated, 1870-1955 ). Includes the by-laws and documents of incorporation from when the company became incorporated in 1902, permissions from producers of patents for the company to use the patent concepts in the manufacture of products, correspondence, reports from consultants on operations at the Waterman Pen Company, and other related materials.
Series II: Product orders and inventories ( undated, 1878-1904, 1941 ). Records consist of agreements between H. P. & E. Day and other companies to supply hard rubber products, and other orders and invoices.
Series III: Property transaction and legal documents ( 1867-1954 ).
Series IV: Financial records ( 1854-1946 ).
Series V: Pens, mechanical pencils, and accessories ( undated, 1879-1950 ).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Day, Julius.; Day, Austin G.; Day, Henry P.; Day, Edmund.; Waterman, Lewis Edson, 1839-1901.
Organizations:
H. P. & E. Day, Inc.; Tingue Manufacturing Company.; New Haven Copper Company.; Austin G. Day Company. (Seymour, Conn.); L. E. Waterman Company
Places:
Seymour, Conn.
Subjects:
Connecticut--Business, industries, and trades--Rubber.; Seymour (Conn.)--Business, industries, and trades--Rubber.; Fountain pens.; L.E. Waterman Company.; Real property--Connecticut.; Pen industry--United States.; Connecticut--Land.; Seymour (Conn.)--Land.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Manuscripts.; Inventories.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the University of Connecticut Libraries in August 1988 by Mr. Robert Scott. Mr. Scott had received the records from his father, R. D. Scott, a former vice-president at Waterman Pen Company in the Seymour, Connecticut, plant.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Administrative records,undated, 1870-1955
  - Incorporation, 1901 (Box 1:1)
  - By-laws, 1901 (Box 1:2)
  - Permission for Henry P. and Edmund Day to use A. G. Day's patent for the manufacture of hard rubber compounds, 1876 (Box 1:3)
  - Permission for H. P. & E. Day and L. E. Waterman Co. to use a patent owned by Charles Nichols for manufacturing fountain pens, 1908 (Box 1:4)
  - Permission for H. P. & E. Day to use a patent of Francis C. Brown for the manufacture of safety fountain pens, 1910 (Box 1:5)
  - Information about patents for fountain pens, 1870-1903 (Box 1:6)
  - Capital stock increase, 1909 (Box 1:7)
  - Certificate of increase of capital stock, 1920 (Box 1:8)
  - Connecticut Bureau of Labor Statistics schedules and State of Connecticut Inspector of Factories report, 1888-1899 (Box 1:9)
  - Correspondence, General, 1887-1953 (Box 1:10)
  - Correspondence, J. H. Nichols (Attorney of Ravenna, Ohio) to Julius Day, 1874 (Box 1:11)
  - Transcript of essay on the history of rubber, undated (Box 1:12)
  - Life insurance policy for Daniel W. Lapham, 1886 (Box 1:13)
  - Proxy, L. E. Waterman to vote for H. P. & E. Day at the meetings of L. E. Waterman Company, 1887 (Box 1:14)
  - Reports, 1948-1955
    - "The Business and Operations of L. E. Waterman Company", written by W. W. Slocum & Company, Engineers, 1948 (Box 1:15)
    - "The Management Organization of L. E. Waterman Company", written by W. W. Slocum & Company, Engineers, 1948 (Box 1:16)
    - "Report on preliminary general survey of L.E. Waterman Company", by Booz, Allen & Hamilton, Consultants, 1951 (Box 1:17)
    - "Management report", Waterman Pen Company, 1953 (Box 1:18)
    - "A Study of the Pen Industry with Relation to the Waterman Pen Co.", 1955 (Box 1:19)
- Series II: Product Orders and Inventories, undated, 1878-1904, 1941
  - Automatic Pen Company (Norwich, Connecticut), 1883 (Box 1:20)
  - Cross Pen Company (Providence, Rhode Island), 1880-1887 (Box 1:21)
  - Davis, Alfred (London, England), 1880 (Box 1:22)
  - Foley, John (New York, New York), 1881 (Box 1:23)
  - D. Mackinnon & Company (New York, New York), 1879-1880 (Box 1:24)
  - L. E. Waterman/ "Ideal" Pen Company, 1884, 1941 (Box 1:25)
  - Wirt, Paul E. (Bloomsburg, Pennsylvania), 1890 (Box 1:26)
  - Inventories of tools, 1878-1879 (Box 1:27)
  - Orders and invoices, undated, 1881-1904 (Box 1:28)
- Series III: Property transaction and legal documents, 1867-1954
  - Brixey, William, 1895-1907 (Box 2:29)
  - Brown, Marie, 1919 (Box 2:30)
  - Brownson, Wendell G., 1907 (Box 2:31)
  - Crowther, Theodore N., 1905 (Box 2:32)
  - Day family, 1867-1907 (Box 2:33)
  - Ford, S. Frederick, 1916 (Box 2:34)
  - French, R. T. and Carlos, and Humphreysville Manufacturing Co., 1896-1945 (Box 2:35)
  - Goodyear, Charles, 1891 (Box 2:36)
  - Marion, Ezra, 1887 (Box 2:37)
  - New Haven Copper Company, 1911-1954 (Box 2:38)
  - Roberts, Eliza M., 1876-1877 (Box 2:39)
  - Tingue Manufacturing Company, 1902-1920 (Box 2:40)
  - United States Pin Company, 1902 (Box 2:41)
  - Wilcoxson family, 1881-1916 (Box 2:42)
- Series IV: Financial records, 1854-1946
  - Accounts
    - Brixey, William, 1892-1903 (Box 2:43)
    - Day, Austin G., Co., 1884-1887 (Box 2:44)
    - Day family, 1876-1887 (Box 2:45)
  - Volumes
    - Balance sheets, 1881-1903 (Box 2:46)
    - Cashbook, 1876-1889 (Box 3)
    - Cashbook, 1924-1946 (Box 4)
    - Daybook, 1866-1882 (Box 2:47)
    - Journal, 1884-1888 (Box 5)
    - Journal, 1889-1908 (Box 6)
    - Ledger, 1854-1866 (Box 7)
    - Ledger, 1876-1884 (Box 8)
    - Receipts, banknotes, etc.,1875-1905 (Box 2:48)
    - Wastebook, 1865-1876 (Box 9)
- Series V: Pens, Mechanical Pencils and Accessories, undated, 1879-1950
  [Detailed descriptions of items were provided by Mr. Robert Astyk of Bellingham, Washington, in July 2003. Items may be viewed only under direct supervision of Archives & Special Collections staff.]
  - Pens, 1885-1918 (Box 10:49)
    - Charles N. Packard #6 dip pen, gothic chased gold filled holder with black hard rubber taper, ca. 1885
    - Caw's N. 301 Safety Pen, #2 Caw's nib, black hard rubber, factory new condition, ca. 1903
    - Waterman 12S Safety Pen, nickel plated clip, scroll engraved gold filled band on barrel, black chased hard rubber, ca. 1908
    - Waterman 18S/48 (barrel end not marked), black smooth hard rubber (gouge near barrel end/packing joint), ca. 1918
  - Mechanical pencils, 1879-1939 [see Note 1] (Box 10:50)
    - Unknown Maker (A.T. Cross?) red/black mottled hard rubber propel pencil, ca. 1879
    - Unknown Maker (A.T. Cross?) black chased hard rubber propel pencil, ca. 1885
    - Waterman JIF [see Note 2] hexagonal sterling silver propel pencil, ca. 1922
    - Waterman JIF [see Note 2] round chased sterling silver propel pencil with 20F price sticker, ca. 1922
    - Waterman 100 Year Supersize Pencil blue (translucent cap top), gold filled trim, propel/repel/expel, 1939
    - Waterman 100 Year Supersize Pencil black, gold filled trim, propel/repel/expel, 1939
  - Mechanical Pencils, 1950 (Box 10:51)
    - Waterman Pencil, black, propel/repel/expel (8 pieces), ca. 1950
  - Gold Pen Nibs, 1904-1944 [see Note 3] (Box 10:52)
    - Caw's #7 fountain pen nib (1 pc.) used, ca. 1904
    - Remex #2 fountain pen nib (1 pc.) used, shank damaged, ca. 1908
    - ALCO #2 [see Note 4] fountain pen nib (1 pc.) used, ca. 1910
    - Waterman #2 fountain pen nibs (8 pcs.), used, various conditions, ca. 1904-1930
    - Waterman #2 fountain pen nib, Canada, used, ca. 1915
    - Waterman #4 fountain pen nibs, used, ca. 1928
    - ALCO ca. fountain pen nibs (2 pcs.), ca. 1930
    - Waterman Standard 100 Year fountain pen nibs (6 pcs.), 1939-1946
    - Waterman Standard 100 Year fountain pen nibs (4 pcs.), damaged (cracks, etc.), 1939-1946
    - Waterman Standard 100 Year fountain pen nibs (2 pcs.), badly damaged, essentially scrap gold, 1939-1946
    - Parker Vacumatic Major fountain pen nib (1 pc.), platinum plating over 14Kt. Gold, badly damaged, essentially scrap gold, 1940
    - Aikin-Lambert Skywriter fountain pen nibs (2 pcs.), steel, 1944
  - Rubber chain of oval links, approximately 36" long, undated (Box 10:53)
  - Waterman's return springs for ball point pens (11 pcs.), ca. 1950 (Box 10:54)
  - Other accessories, 1915-1950 (Box 10:55)
    - gold filled, engraved barrel band for fountain pen (1 pc.), ca. 1915
    - wide cap band for Citation Taperite pencil, gold filled (1 pc.), 1946-1950
    - Waterman's ball point refills, Red ink, boxed (2 pcs.), ca. 1950
    - Waterman's ball point refills, Blue ink(?), not boxed (1 pc.), ca. 1950
    - Waterman's adjustable erasers (2 envelopes of 3 each), ca. 1950
  - Notes, provided by Mr. Robert Astyk:
    *Note 1: A.G. Day and H. P. & E. Day Cos. had a "Pencil Division." Day may have marketed its own pencils though this is less likely than simply producing the parts for others. The elaborate "rope" knurled rings and turnings argue for a date at or before 1880.
    *Note 2: Waterman-JIF was formed in 1926 as an independent though related pen company by Jules Fagard who obtains all distrubution rights for France, Belgium and their colonies. Fagard became French sub-agent for Sloane in 1915.
    *Note 3: Even when not so marked, fountain pen nibs were customarily made (in the U.S.A.) of 14Kt. Gold. All nibs marked "Waterman" or Caw's" are 14Kt. Exceptions are noted in the listing.
    *Note 4: ALCO, Aikin-Lambert Co., was a maker of high quality gold pen nibs for dip pens from the mid 19th century. As Waterman's sales expanded in the 1890s Aikin-Lambert became a contract supplier of nibs for Waterman along with it's primary source, Leroy Fairchild. Circa 1903 Aikin-Lambert supplanted Fairchild as primary source. At an indeterminate time, most likely between 1905 and 1910, Waterman acquired Aikin-Lambert, moving nib making operations in-house. Waterman used the name Aikin-Lambert and the acronym, ALCO, as sub-brands through the 1940s.